Guide to the Southern United States Manuscript Map Collection, 1850-1923 and undated RL.11492
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southern United States manuscript map collection
1850-1923 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11492
14 Linear Feet 33 items
Comprises 33 sketch maps of locations in Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, and West Virginia. Includes a number of B. P. Baker Co. plats for a tract of land in Gates Co., N.C.; plans of subdivisions and improvements in Savannah by Percy Sugden; a map of Durham, N.C., in 1867 by Lewis Blount; a map of Mississippi representing Indian territories and missionary stations by Sarah Coffin; and a detailed plat of the Bennett & Wallace Lands in West Virginia. Maps signed by Robert Jayne, W. F. Brown, John Tebeau, and Ravenel Gignilliet are present. Primarily drawn ink on paper. Sizes of maps vary between 11x 14 cm. to 70 x 104 cm.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Southern United States Manuscript Map Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1992.
Collection Overview
Comprises 33 sketch maps of locations in Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, and West Virginia. Includes a number of B. P. Baker Co. plats for a tract of land in Gates Co., N.C.; plans of subdivisions and improvements in Savannah by Percy Sugden; a map of Durham, N.C., in 1867 by Lewis Blount; a map of Mississippi representing Indian territories and missionary stations by Sarah Coffin; and a detailed plat of the Bennett & Wallace Lands in West Virginia. Maps signed by Robert Jayne, W. F. Brown, John Tebeau, and Ravenel Gignilliet are present. Primarily drawn ink on paper. Sizes of maps vary between 11x 14 cm. to 70 x 104 cm.
Florida -- Maps; Georgia -- Maps; Louisiana -- Maps; Mississippi -- Maps; North Carolina -- Maps; Savannah (Ga.) -- Maps; South Carolina -- Maps; Virginia -- Maps; Manuscript maps; Sketch maps; Blount, Lewis; Brown, W. F.; Coffin, Sarah; De Saulles, A. B.; Gignilliet, Ravenel; Jayne, Robert; Sugden, Percy; Tebeau, John R.
- Florida
  - "Plan of Ravenswood Florida", undated.; 58 x 78 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Plat representing lots as well as Lake Dorr and a railroad. Ink and watercolors on paper.
- Georgia
  - "Plan of Forty-five lots lying...Southeast of the City of Savannah....", 1869.; Scale 1 inch:5 chains. 97 x 59 cm (Oversize-folder 2)
    Tebeau, John. Plat in colored ink on paper.
  - "Map representing that part of Bonaventure lying between Evergreen Cemetery [Chatham Co.]....", 1881.; Scale 1":100'. 58 x 72 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Tebeau, John R. Plat showing 23 lots. Colored ink and watercolors on linen. (Three copies, including the original.)
  - "Plan of the Proposed Widening of that Portion of Waters Rd. [Savannah]....", 1892; Scale 1":100'. 24 x 26 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Sugden, Percy. Survey map. Note on verso. Ink on linen.
  - "Plan Showing Encroachments Extending Beyond the Proposed Eastern Line of Waters Road [Savannah]....", 1892.; Scale, 1":50'. 31 x 94 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Sugden, Percy. Showing properties and electric railway, with notations. Colored ink on paper.
  - "Plan of a portion of Anderson St. [Savannah]....", 1893.; Scale 1":200'. 16 x 48 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Sugden, Percy. Ink on linen.
  - "Plan of subdivision of No. 3...belonging to the Merchants and Mechanics Land Co. [Savannah].", 1896.; 29 x 59 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Sugden, Percy. Plat showing streets, roads, and railroads. Note on verso. Ink and watercolors on paper.
  - "Plan of that portion of Tybee Island [Chatham Co.]....", 1897.; Scale 1":200'. 50 x 95 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Sugden, Percy. Plat showing lots as well as streets and waterways. Ink and watercolor on paper.
  - "Plan of Subdivision No. 5 of the Merchants and Mechanics Land Co. [Savannah]....", 1898; 46 x 62 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Sugden, Percy. Plat showing 11 lots as well as streets. Ink and watercolor on paper.
  - "Plan of Subdivision No. 6 of the lands of the Merchants and Mechanics Land Co. [Savannah]....", 1898; Scale 1":120'. 67 x 86 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Sugden, Percy. Plat showing roads and streets, with notations. Ink on linen.
  - "Dr. Falligant's Map of the Village of Eastland....", 1898.; 67 x 99 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Brucker, E. "Dr. Falligant's Map of the Village of Eastland…." Plat showing 378 lots on the southeast border of Savannah. Colored ink on paper reinforced with cloth.
  - "Map showing Levy Avenue....", 1900.; Scale 1":400'. 46 x 37 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Brown, W. F. Depicts roads, hammocks, and a cemetery. Colored ink on linen.
  - "Plan of a tract of land situate 3 miles from the City of Savannah...as surveyed for John C. Rowland, Esq.", 1900.; 60 x 93 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Sugden, Percy. Map showing waterways, roads, railway, and adjacent plantations as well as representing forests and fields. Ink and watercolors on paper reinforced with cloth.
  - "Map of Henry Street East From Waters Road [Savannah]....", 1905.; Scale 1":200'. 14 x 65 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Brown, W. F. Ink on linen.
  - "Plat of Portion of Rowland Tract Chatham Co. Ga. surveyed for M. H. Floyd Esq.", 1919.; Scale 1":400'. 59 x 28 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Gignilliet, Ravenel. Colored ink on linen.
- Louisiana
  - Map primarily representing Lake Pontchartrain, Lake Borgne, the Gulf of Mexico...., undated; 70 x 104 cm. (Oversize-folder 2)
    Map primarily representing Lake Pontchartrain, Lake Borgne, the Gulf of Mexico, and the Mississippi River as well as New Orleans and Biloxi. Colored ink on paper reinforced with cloth.
  - Map of part of New Orleans showing plans of lands on Bayou St. and on Lake Pontchartrain, undated; 33 x 63 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    "Lands of Gentilly" (verso). Pencil and ink on paper.
- Mississippi
  - "Map of the District North of Aberdeen" (verso), 1879; 51 x 47 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    De Saulles, A. B. Sketch map in colored ink on paper, showing towns, waterways and roads, and a railroad.
  - "Aged 11" (verso), undated; 14 x 11 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Coffin, Sarah E. Map showing counties in the lower part of the state and showing the territories of the Chickasaw and Choctaw Indians. In these territories, a missionary station, agencies, and villages are represented. Colored ink on paper.
- North Carolina
  - "Dempsey L. Sumner bought of Thos. H. Cross...", 1902; 1 inch:4 chains. 45 x 77 cm. (Oversize-folder 1)
    Gates Co. B. P. Baker, Co., Surveyor. Plat in colored ink on linen.
  - "A part of 'Farmer's Delight' surveyed for Scott Melton.", 1902; 1 inch:4 chains. 42 x 33 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Gates Co. B. P. Baker, Co., Surveyor. Colored ink on linen.
  - "A Section of 'Farmer's Delight' cut for John E. Folk.", 1903; Scale 1 inch:4 chains. 39 x 27 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Gates Co. B. P. Baker, Co., Surveyor. Ink on paper.
  - "Portion of 'Farmer's Delight'....", 1903; Scale 1 inch:4 chains. 53 x 49 cm. (Oversize-folder 1)
    Gates Co. B. P. Baker, Co., Surveyor. Plat in colored in linen.
  - "This map of Durham as I remembered in 1867-1868....", 1923; 59 x 75 cm. Reproduction copy included (58 x 59 cm.). (Oversize-folder 1)
    Blount, Lewis. Showing properties, R. F. Morris Tobacco factory, and other sites noted by numbers coordinated with list on the map. Ink on paper.
  - Map of roads in Orange, Wake, Johnston, Nash, Edgecomb, Halifax, Franklin, Warren, Granville, and Person Counties, 1796; 55 x 70 cm. (Oversize-folder 1)
    K. L. Colored ink on paper mounted on board.
  - Map showing towns, roads, a railroad, and county seats in Randolph, Chatham, Orange, Guilford, Alamance, Rockingham, Person, and Caswell counties, 1865; 56 x 60 cm. (Oversize-folder 1)
    K.L. Map showing towns, roads, a railroad, and county seats in Randolph, Chatham, Orange, Guilford, Alamance, Rockingham, Person, and Caswell counties possibly around 1865. Ink on paper mounted on board.
  - Map primarily showing land of Louis John H. Livermore, undated; 29 x 42 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Gates Co. Ink on linen.
- South Carolina
  - "Plan of five hundred and twenty four acres situate on Beach Hill, St. Paul's parish...", 1850; 30 x 47 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Ink on linen, with green border.
  - "Plan of one hundred acres of land on Beach Hill of St. Paul's parish. Cobleton Dis't....", 1850; Scale 2 inches:10 chains. 27 x 23 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Jayne, Robert K. Ink on linen, with green border.
  - "Beaufort District, So. Ca.", undated; 20 x 32 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Map showing the coast, islands and Savannah. Pencil on paper.
- Virginia
  - "Map of south central Virginia....", 1875; Scale 1":10'. 21 x 32 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Map of south central Virginia, primarily Henry, Franklin, Bedford, Pittsylvania, Campbell, Appomattox, Prince Edwards, Lunenberg, Charlotte, and Mecklenburg Counties showing railroads, and coal and iron deposits. Ink and watercolors on paper.
  - "The Metropolitan Line Washington to Augusta, Ga.", undated; 25 x 17 cm. (Oversize-folder 4)
    Ink on paper.
- West Virginia
  - "Plat of Bennett & Wallace Lands in Gilmer, Braxton & Calhoun Counties West Virginia.", 1880; Scale 1 inch:200 poles. 58 x 45 cm. (Oversize-folder 3)
    Shows roads, railroad, and waterways. Colored ink and watercolors on linen.